"Drug Residues in Meat and
Their Effect on Antibiotic Resistance"
According to
the World Health Organization,
more antibiotics
are fed to farm animals
to prevent disease
and fatten them faster
than are used
to treat sick people.
This can foster the growth of
antibiotic-resistant superbugs
that can then get
transmitted to humans.
As the UK's
Chief Medical Officer
once put it,
"Every inappropriate
or unnecessary use
in animals or agriculture
is potentially signing
a death warrant
for a future patient.”
So, what are they:
miracle drugs or pig food?
Here's how Dr. Greger
framed the issue
in a debate he had
with industry representatives,
including from the
National Pork Producers Council.
To ask if there's a question
between human drug resistance
and livestock antibiotic use
is like asking if there's
human-induced climate change,
or if there's a link
between smoking and lung cancer.
There are a few dissenting
industry scientists on one side,
but then, basically,
every other scientist
on the other.
Both opposing camps
have scientists on their side,
but only one really has
science on their side.
One can just look at who's
on the sides of this debate.
In one corner,
you have
the World Health Organization,
the American Medical
Association,
the American Academy
of Pediatrics,
American Public Health
Association,
another 100
medical and public health
organizations in the country.
On the other side,
you have
the National Turkey Federation,
the National Chicken Council,
the Sheep Industry Association,
the National Pork Producers.
It could not be more stark.
Previously, Dr. Greger discussed
how feeding millions of pounds
of antibiotics
to cows, pigs, and chickens
every year is dangerous,
because it fosters
antibiotic resistance--
not necessarily
because there's a problem
with antibiotic drug residues
getting into the meat itself.
But, turns out,
he may be wrong.
In 2010,
the U.S. Inspector General
slammed the U.S.
Department of Agriculture
for not protecting
the American public
from the contamination of meat
with residual drugs,
pesticides, and heavy metals.
These drug and chemical residues
then find their way
to our dinner plates.
But in order to safeguard
the nation's food supply
from harmful residues,
the USDA,
Food and Drug Administration,
and Environmental
Protection Agency
are supposed to test
for these contaminants,
and prevent adulterated meat
from entering the food supply.
But, based on their review,
the U.S. Inspector General
found that
the National Residue Program
is not accomplishing its mission
of monitoring the food supply
for harmful residues.
Regulators hadn't even
established threshold values
for many dangerous substances,
which has resulted
in contaminated meat
being distributed to consumers.
What potential effects
could the drugs
and toxic metals in meat
have on people who consume it?
Gastrointestinal bleeding,
ulcers, allergic reactions,
serious nerve damage,
severe inflammation,
skin cancers,
internal cancers, jaundice,
kidney failure,
neurotoxicity, and even death.
Doesn't cooking
destroy the drugs, though?
No.
No amount of cooking
will destroy residues.
In fact, in some cases,
heat may actually
break residues down
into components that are even
more harmful to consumers.
The Pew Charitable Trusts
point out
that chemicals
that experts agree
pose a significant
public health hazard
are not routinely tested for,
while others
that pose little risk
are routinely included
in sampling plans.
The USDA does test
for some hazardous drugs though,
and found that only about
1 in 260 samples
of animal products
had drug residue violations.
But that suggests more than
100 million pounds of meat
adulterated with drugs
is served up every year
in the United States alone.